Let's move on to our next exercise where we will explore the Less language.
接下来让我们进行 Less 的练习吧
I know you are looking at that and saying I wish my doctor would say that to me.
我相信你会看着 "Exercise Less" 并在心底希冀自己的导师也能这么说
Tough luck, my friends, in real life, you have to exercise most.
残念的是 少年 在现实生活中 你必须要进行很多练习
But let's talk about exercise Less.
咳 玩笑到此为止 让我们正式开始练习使用
Now, the pre-processors.
Less 这个 CSS 的预处理器
Now open your project in brackets or the text editor of your choice, and
现在先用 Brackets 或你喜欢的文本编辑器 打开我们至今为止做的网站项目
then go to the CSS folder and create a file named mystyles.less.
然后进入到 CSS 文件夹并创建 一个叫 mystyles.less 的文件
After that, we'll add some Less code into this file.
我们将会在该文件中加进一些 Less 代码
First, let me define some variables that we're gonna use in the coat.
首先 让我定义几个变量
You can see that now I have added a few variables here.
你可以看到我在这定义了几个变量
I have defined several colors there and then also a height variable there.
我定义了好几种颜色变量 和一个高度变量
I'm gonna make use of these in defining my Less classes later.
我将会在之后的 Less 类中应用到它们
Next, I add in a Less class, which I am going to use as a mixin.
接下来 我加进了一个 Less 类 以展示混入的使用
And I'm naming this Less class as zero-margin.
我将该 Less 类命名为了 zero-margin
You have seen this example already in the lecture previously.
我相信你已经在之前某节课中 看到过这个类
So for this I have given two parameters, pad-up-dn and pad-left-right.
那么这个类将接受两个参数 pad-up-dn 和 pad-left-right
And I'm using them to define the padding for this class here.
从字面意思即可知 我将应用它们 来定义该类对应的填充样式
I'm gonna make use of this class as a mixin for
我将会把这个类作为混入的素材
defining several of the role classes.
来定义一些 row 相关的类
Next, using the mixin, I am defining several of
那么于此 你能看到我定义了 好几个 row 相关的类
the row classes that I'm using in my project.
我将会在我们的项目中使用它们
So here you can see that I am defining a row header class with zero margin
你可以看到 这几个类的代码的第一行
asterisk.
都是对 zero-margin 类的引用
When I have the final row content class with zero margin with parameters 50px,
然后在最后这里的设置了 zero-margin 参数为 50px 和 0px 的 row-content
0px and then row-footer and the jumbotron.
和设置了参数为 20px 和 0px 的 row-footer 之后 我还定义了一个 jumbotron 类
So for each of these, the padding values are different, but
总之对不同的角色 我定义了 不同的填充数值
the margin value is still 0px auto.
不过我把它们的边缘数值都设置为了 0
So I am able to make use of the mixin class, and
总之有了混入之后
then define these classes using that other class that we have defined earlier.
我就能重复利用代码了
Next I define a carousel class.
接下来我定义了一个 carousel 类 来定制我的轮播
In the carousel class,
在该类中
notice the use of the variables that we have defined already.
我用到了我之前定义的某些变量
So for the background I'm setting it as dark-indigo.
比如将背景色设为 dark-indigo 这个变量
For item, I am setting the height as carousel-height.
将其下的 item 的高度设为 carousel-height 这个变量
And then the image also I am setting
然后对再其下的 img 的最小高度 也设置为了 carousel-height 这个变量
Note also how I am using nesting in order to define these three classes.
需要注意的是 这里我用了嵌套 来同时定义了三个类
So the item class is inside the carousel class, and
也就是在 carousel 中嵌了 item
the image class is inside the item class.
在 item 中嵌了 img
So when it is combined we're going to have three different classes.
也就是说这段 Less 代码编译成 可用的 CSS 代码后
The dark carousel class, the dark carousel.item, and
会变成三段代码 每一段代码 定义了这三个类中的一个
then the dark carousel.item and image classes.
分别是 .carousel, .carousel .item 和 .carousel .item .img 类
Here is yet another nesting of classes.
这个则是另一个使用嵌套的栗子
This is what I use for the navbar inverse.
我用其来定制我的 navbar-inverse
Now, you're beginning to realize that I am defining the Less class
你可能已经注意到 这些 Less 代码 定制出来的 CSS 类
corresponding to the CSS class that we have already constructed.
正是之前我们定义过的 CSS 类
Now the reason for
我这么做的原因
this, is to see how from a Less class you can go to a CSS class.
是想让你知道 Less 和 CSS 之间的关系
So it is more easier for
从而今后如果你想用 Less 来定制你的网页时
you to understand once you know what the CSS class looks like.
只要你知道 CSS 该怎么写
So that in the future if you want to use Less,
你就能更轻易地将其转换成
you will easily know how to make use of it from this experience.
相应的 Less 代码
So here, I am defining the .navbar-inverse class, and
总之在这 我定义了一个 navbar-inverse 类
inside there I am listing other classes like the .navbar-nav>.active>a and
然后在其下 我定义了一系列的类
other classes you can see me defining here.
诸如 .navbar-nav>.active>a 和 其它的一些类
Finally, I add in those CSS classes for
然后最后 我定义了一些类 这些类看上去和之前的
which I could not use the Less features into a large extent.
CSS 版本的类差不多
So these are standard CSS classes.
事实上 由于这些类相对独立
They have nothing in common with the remaining classes.
既无法让它们利用已有代码 也无法重复利用它们的代码
So I am not able to use either mixins, or
所以像混入 嵌套这样的 Less 的特色
to use their nesting for these CSS classes.
在它们这里起不了作用
I'm still using the variables that I have defined earlier.
当然了 我还是利用到了一些变量
So you can see that I am using some of the color variables
比如这个 tab-content 类中的颜色属性
that I have defined earlier to define these classes.
我就用到了 lt-gray 这个变量
Once you complete this, you are now going to save this Less file,
当你保存好这份 Less 文件
and then compile this Less file into the corresponding CSS file.
并将其编译成可用的 CSS 文件时
Now once we compile this Less file
你会发现编译出来的这份 CSS 文件
You will notice that the CSS file is the same as the CSS file that we had,
和我们之前使用的 CSS 文件
had constructed for this project.
一致无二
How do we compile the Less file into the corresponding CSS file?
那么怎么才能编译 Less 文件呢 ?
Now, this is where I'm going to make use of a node module called Less.
我们需要用到一个叫 Less 的
We are going to install this node module as a global module.
全局 node 模块
To do that, on your command
为了安装这个模块
prompt you're going to type
你需要在命令行中
npm install minus g and Less.
运行 npm install -g less
The minus g flag is to indicate, to any member,
其中 -g 是全局模块的标识
that, this module should be installed as a global module
意味着正在安装的这个模块
to be available for use in any project that we create.
将能被任何项目引用
Now, of course the Less compiler we will be using in many projects.
而毋庸置疑的是, Less 编译器 很有可能在很多项目中有用
So that's why I'm installing this as a global MPM module.
所以我们要用 -g 这个标识
Now if you are doing this on a Mac or
如果你是在 Mac 或者 Linux 上 进行这个步骤的话
on a Linux, you may wish to proceed this with the sudo command, S-U-D-O.
你需要在这行命令的开头 加上 sudo 这四个字母
On a Windows machine, you don't need that.
如果你用的是 Windows 就不用加
But since I am running this on a Mac, I'm gonna proceed thus with a pseudo-command.
由于我现在用的是 Mac 所以我要加上 sudo
And then when you hit the return, on a Mac or
然后如果你用的是 Mac 或是 Linux
Linux it expects you to type in your password to let you install.
你还需要输一下密码
So this is giving admin privileges so that the package can be installed correctly.
否则你的优先级不足以让你完成 安装全局模块这个操作
On a Windows machine, this is not required.
而在 Windows 上则不需要输密码
You just type npm install minus g Less.
不像 Mac 和 Linux 这么麻烦
And then, npm will go and fetch the Less module
然后一切妥当后
from the global repository of the npm modules.
npm 会帮你部署好这个模块
Now, this installation of the Less module will
那么为什么要安装这个模块呢 ? 因为它提供了一个叫
make available to us a compiler called lessc.
lessc 的编译器给我们
This compiler will be available to us on the command line.
这个编译器是在命令行使用的
So if you want to compile a Less file,
如果你想编译一个 Less 文件
then you would just type Less c space and the name of the Less file.
你只需在命令行中键入 lessc xxx 即可 其中 xxx 是你的 Less 文件名
And then this will automatically compile and
然后 lessc 将会自动帮你完成编译
then output that corresponding CSS file.
并生成一个相应的 CSS 文件
Let's see that in action.
让我们实际操作一下吧
At the prompt I type in lessc
你可以看到我键入了
mystyles.less and
lessc mystyles.less
when I hit the return it is going to generate the corresponding CSS file.
然后当我敲回车 它就会 生成相应的 CSS 代码
Now, you can see that the CSS file has been printed out on the console directly.
你还可以看到在命令行这里 生成的 CSS 代码被直接打印了出来
Now, I wanna capture this inside a CSS file here.
接下来 如果我想将这些代码
So to do that.
利用 mystyle.less 的话
First, I'm going to move my existing mystyles.css file into another file so
我需要先将已有的 mystyle.css 文件
that I will save my existing mystyles.css file before overwriting
移到另一个文件夹
this with the compile file that is produced by Less c compiler.
从而避免它被 mystyle.less 生成出来的 mystyle.css 文件覆盖
If you know how to use the command line, you can simply say move mystyles.css.
如果你对命令行很熟悉 你可以在命令行中完成移动这个操作
On a Mac or Linux, you can do this.
在 Mac 和 Linux 上都是可以这样做的
Now on Windows, you can use the rename command on the command line.
如果在 Windows 上 你可以如图所示般 重命名你想移动的 mystyle.css 这个文件
Next, I'm going to type in lessc mystyles.less, and
接下来 我将输入 lessc mystyle.less > mystyle.css
then pipe this value into mystyles.css file.
这将会把生成的相应的 CSS 代码
And then, this will save the output from the Less c
塞进 mystyle.css 这个文件中
compiler into the CSS file, here.
然后 系统会自动把 mystyle.css 从 lessc 编译器中移到你的硬盘上
Now, at the end of this, you can open the CSS file and
然后最后 你可以打开这个 CSS 文件
see the compiled corresponding CSS file for the Less file that we just created.
并看看里面的代码长啥样
Having a look at the CSS file that has been generated for
当你打开这个 CSS 文件
us we will see that this CSS file is pretty much similar
你可以看到这和我们之前用的 CSS 文件
to the CSS file we had constructed earlier.
长得非常像
So now you see the advantage of using Less to
所以到此为止 我们学习了如何利用 Less 的优点
define your CSS classes using the Less syntax.
来定义一系列的 CSS 类
And then automatically generating the CSS classes by compiling the Less file.
然后我们学习了如何编译 Less 代码
This completes this exercise, where we learned how to write Less code and
以上 我们完成了这次练习 我们不仅学习了 Less 代码怎么写
then automatically generating the CSS from the Less code using the CSS compiler.
还学习了如何去编译它 【翻译 - Carefree0910】